Guide to the Matthew Josephson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1917-1979; Series I; 4.5; (11 boxes)
  - Lowenthal, Max, 1934-65, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 179)
  - Lubin, Isador (Box 7, Folder 180)
    See also: Box 16, folders 374-82
  - Lynd, Robert, 1937-43, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 181)
  - "M" general, 1928-78, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 182-85)
  - McKenney, Ruth, 1937-71, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 186-88)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1932, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - MacKenzie, Norman, 1951-76 (Box 7, Folder 190)
  - Maltz, Albert, 1948-61 (Box 7, Folder 191)
  - McWilliams, Carey (Box 7, Folder 192-93)
    See also: Box 5, folders 109-11
  - Martin, Jay, 1941-70, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 194)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 195)
  - Metzler, Martin, 1967-70 (Box 8, Folder 196)
  - Miller, Dorothy C., 1943-73 (Box 8, Folder 197)
  - Miller, Henry (Box 8, Folder 198)
    See also: Box 17, folders 403-06
  - The Minnesota Review (Box 8, Folder 199)
    See also: Box 6, folders 136-38
  - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo, [1925?]-38 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1925, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 201)
  - Moses, Robert, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 202)
  - Mumford, Lewis (Box 8, Folder 203)
    See also: Box 7, folders 192-93
  - "N" general, 1936-78 (Box 8, Folder 204)
  - The Nation (Box 8, Folder 205)
  - National Institute of Arts & Letters, 1947-73 (Box 8, Folder 206)
  - Noutra, Richard, 1953-63 (Box 8, Folder 207)
  - The New Republic (Box 8, Folder 208)
    See also: Box 20, folder 472
  - The New Yorker (Box 8, Folder 209-11)
    See also: Box 20, folders 475, 477
  - Nossiter, Bernard D., 1964-66, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 212)
  - "O" general, 1928-59 (Box 8, Folder 213)
  - O'Conner, Harvey (Box 8, Folder 214-15)
    See also: Box 14, folder 352
  - Orlovitz, Gil, 1965-67, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 216)
  - "P" general, 1931-76, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 217-18)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1938-47 (Box 8, Folder 219)
  - Perlo, Victor, 1972, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 220)
  - Phillips, Melba, 1947-59, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 221)
  - Pierce, Waldo, 1939-41, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 222-24)
  - Piel, Gerard (Box 8, Folder 225)
    See also: Box 16, folders 387-91
  - Porter, Katharine Anne (Box 8, Folder 226-28)
    See also: Box 4, folders 103-05
  - Provisional Committee for Cuba, 1935-36 (Box 9, Folder 229)
  - Powell, Thomas Reed (Box 9, Folder 230)
    See also: Box 4, folder 93
  - Quinn, T. K., 1955-57 (Box 9, Folder 231)
  - "R" general, 1934-77, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 232-33)
  - Rabinowitz, Louis M., Foundation, 1961-63, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 234)
  - Rahon, Alice, 1962-63, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 235)
  - Rattner, Abraham, 1939-75, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 236-37)
  - Rhodes, Peter (Box 9, Folder 238)
  - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1937-44, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 239)
  - Russell & Russell Publishers, 1954-55, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 240)
  - "S" general, 1930-74, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 241-45)
  - Sarason, Bertram, 1969-73 (Box 9, Folder 246)
  - The Saturday Evening Post, 1943-61 (Box 9, Folder 247)
  - Saturday Review, 1932-58 (Box 9, Folder 248)
  - Schappes, Morris U., 1932-49 (Box 9, Folder 249)
  - Schneider, Isador, 1926-77, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 250)
  - Shapley, Harlow, 1947-48 (Box 9, Folder 251)
  - Sheeler, Charles, 1933-61, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 252)
  - Sheridan House, Inc., 1942 (Box 9, Folder 253)
  - Shi, David (Box 9, Folder 254)
    See also: Box 14, folders 344-45
  - Shipman, Evan, 1931-45, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 255)
  - Simon & Schuster, Inc. (Box 10, Folder 256)
    See also: Box 4, folder 89
  - Smith College, 1971-72 (Box 10, Folder 257)
  - Smith, John Chabot, 1975, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 258)
  - Society of American Historians, Inc., 1960-74 (Box 10, Folder 259)
  - Sonnenberg, Benjamin, 1943-46 (Box 10, Folder 260)
  - Soupault, Philippe, 1925-76, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 261-63)
  - Soupault, Ré, 1943-46 (Box 10, Folder 264)
  - The Southern Review (Box 10, Folder 265-66)
    See also: Box 20, folders 478, 481
  - Sproul, Allen (Box 10, Folder 267)
    See also: Box 7, folder 165
  - Steegmiller, Francis, 1946-70, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 268)
  - Steichen, Edward, 1942-44, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 269)
  - Stone, I. F., 1937-39, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 270)
  - Strauss, Michael W., 1962-63 (Box 10, Folder 271)
  - Sweezy, Paul, 1956, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 272)
  - Symington, Stuart, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 273)
  - "T" general, 1930-63, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 274)
  - Tate, Allen, 1959-62 (Box 10, Folder 275)
  - Thompson, Charles Willis (Box 10, Folder 276)
    See also: Box 17, folders 419-22
  - Triolet, Elsa (Box 10, Folder 277)
    See also: Box 1, folders 6-7
  - Tugwell, Rexford G., 1962-63 (Box 10, Folder 278)
  - Turnball, Andrew, 1961-62 (Box 10, Folder 279)
  - "U-V" general, 1924-66, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 280)
  - University of Wyoming, 1960-78, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 281)
  - The Virginia Quarterly Review (Box 10, Folder 282)
    See also: Box 6, folders 136-38; Box 20, folder 466
  - "W" general, 1919-77, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 283-84)
  - Weinstein, Allen, 1975-76, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 285)
  - Weston, Christine, 1939-44 (Box 11, Folder 286-87)
  - Wheelwright, John Brooks, 1923-33, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 288)
  - Whitman, Alden, 1967-77 (Box 11, Folder 289)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1942-30 (Box 11, Folder 290)
  - Witt, Nathan, 1944-63 (Box 11, Folder 291)
  - Woodward, C. Vann, 1938-70, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 292)
  - Worth, Joan, 1965-75, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 293)
  - "Y-Z" general, 1947-72 (Box 11, Folder 294)
  - Young, Robert R., 1944-49 (Box 11, Folder 295)
  - Zeligs, Meyer, 1962-67 (Box 11, Folder 296)
  - Zilliacus, Konni, 1949-62, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 297)
  - Zugsmith, Leane, 1946-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 298)
  - Unidentified, 1919-75, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 299)
- Journals, 1934-1976; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  The journals in Series II are chronologically arranged.
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 300-01)
    See also: Box 17, folders 413-15, 419-22
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 302-06)
    See also: Box 4, folder 95; Box 18, folders 442-43; Box 20, folder 473
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 307)
    See also: Box 13, folders 334-35, 353
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 308)
    See also: Box 13, folders 342-43; Box 18,folders 436-40; Box 19, folders 445-50
  - Journal, [1950-59?] (Box 12, Folder 309-11)
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 312-13)
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 314-17)
    See also: Box 17, folders 395-401
  - Journal (Box 12, Folder 318)
    See also: Box 16, folders 374-82; Box 17, folders 408-11
  - Journal, 1973-76, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 319-21)
- Subject Files, 1921-1978; Series III; 1; (3 boxes)
  Boxes 13-15 hold Series III, Subject Files, which are arranged alphabetically by title or subject. Titles established by Josephson are in quotations.
  - Aesthete, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 322)
  - Aragon, Louis, 1944-61, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 323)
  - "Aspects of the Thirties", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 324)
  - Breton, André, 1960, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 325)
  - Broom, 1921-73, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 326-30)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1930, 1944, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 331)
  - Dadaism (Box 13, Folder 332)
  - The Depression, 1932-33, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 333)
  - "Europe Revisited" (Box 13, Folder 334-35)
  - First American Writers Conference, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 336)
  - Hiss, Alger (Box 13, Folder 337)
    See also: Box 6, folder 144
  - "Individualism Intensified in Isolated Cases" (Box 13, Folder 338)
  - Insull, Samuel (Box 13, Folder 339)
    See also: Edison and The Money Lords, Box 17, folder 408
  - "Iron Curtain", 1948-49 (Box 13, Folder 340)
  - Italy, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 341)
  - Josephson, Matthew, 1950-55, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 342-43)
  - Josephson, Matthew (Box 14, Folder 344-45)
    See also: Box 9, folder 254
  - Literary Art in America, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 346)
  - "The Machine Age", n.d. (Box 14, Folder 347-48)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 349-51)
  - O'Conner, Harvey, 1953, 1978, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 352)
  - "Paris Revisited", 1934 (Box 14, Folder 353)
  - Poetry, 1925-28, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 354)
  - Russia, 1933-34, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 355-56)
  - "The Russian-German Pact", 1934, 1939, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 357)
  - Sheeler, Charles (Box 14, Folder 358-59)
    See also: box 9, folder 252
  - Social Economic Plan, 1935, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 360)
  - Soupault, Philippe, 1941-45, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 361-63)
  - Spain, 1934, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 364)
  - "Technocracy", 1935, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 365)
  - transition, 1924, 1928, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 366)
  - The Tyrol, notes on, 1922, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 367)
  - "Un-American Activites" (Box 15, Folder 368)
    See also: Box 13, folders 342-43
  - Valéry, Paul, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 369)
  - Wilson, Edmund (Box 15, Folder 370-71)
  - Women, notes on, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 372)
  - "Yaddo Conference", 1931 (Box 15, Folder 373)
- Writings, 1926-1977; Series IV; 2; (5 boxes)
  Series IV, Writings is divided into two sections, Books and Articles. The papers in the Books section are arranged alphabetically by title and material on each work has been placed in the following order: correspondence, research materials, notes, manuscripts, galley proofs, and papers. Unidentified works are at the end of this section. Articles are arranged alphabetically by subject and title. Miscellaneous speeches, editorials, and unidentified fragments are placed at the end of the section.
  - BOOKS
    - Al Smith: Hero of the Cities
      - Correspondence (Box 16, Folder 374-82)
        See also: Box 8, folder 202
      - Research Materials, 1926-67, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 383)
      - Notes, 1969, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 384)
      - Galley proofs and papers, 1967-69, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 385)
    - The Big Guns: The Road to Garrison State
      - Correspondence and notes (Box 16, Folder 386)
        See also: Box 3, folder 76; Box 8, folder 205; Box 10, folder 272
    - Edison
      - Correspondence (Box 16, Folder 387-91)
        See also: Box 9, folder 248
      - Manuscripts [fragments], n.d. (Box 16, Folder 392)
      - Papers, 1956-75, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 393)
    - Empire of the Air
      - Correspondence and papers, 1943-71, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 394)
    - Infidel in the Temple
      - Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 395-401)
        See also:Box 3, folder 49; Box 7, folder 166; Box 9, folder 234
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 402)
    - Life Among the Surrealists
      - Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 403-06)
        See also: Box 10, folder 275
      - Papers, 1961-65 (Box 17, Folder 407)
    - The Money Lords
      - Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 408-11)
        See also: Box 20, folder 473
      - Papers, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 412)
    - The Politicoes
      - Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 413-15)
        See also: Box 5, folder 118
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 416)
    - Portrait of the Artist as American
      - Correspondence, 1930-36 (Box 17, Folder 417)
      - Manuscripts [fragments], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 418)
    - The President Makers
      - Correspondence (Box 17, Folder 419-22)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 423)
      - Manuscripts [fragments] and galley proofs, 1963, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 424)
    - The Robber Barons
      - Correspondence (Box 18, Folder 425-33)
      - Papers, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 434)
    - Rousseau
      - Correspondence and papers, 1931-38 (Box 18, Folder 435)
    - Sidney Hillman: Statesman of Labor
      - Correspondence (Box 18, Folder 436-40)
        See also: Box 3, folder 76; Box 8, folder 209-11
      - Papers, 1944-54, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 441)
    - Stendhal: The Pursuit of Happiness
      - Correspondence (Box 18, Folder 442-43)
        See also: Box 3, folder 76; Box 7, folder 171
      - Papers, 1942, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 444)
    - Union House, Union Bar
      - Correspondence, 1943-56, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 445-50)
      - Papers, 1956, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 451)
    - Victor Hugo
      - Correspondence (Box 19, Folder 452-54)
        See also: Box 3, folder 76
      - Papers, 1942, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 455)
    - Zola and his Time
      - Correspondence (Box 19, Folder 456-57)
      - Papers, 1928, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 458)
      - "The Life of Émile Zola" (movie), 1937, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 459-62)
    - Unidentified Titles
      - Chapters on labor, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 463)
      - Chapters on Russia, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 464)
  - ARTICLES
    - America's Secret Axis, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 465)
    - Beard, Charles, profile on (Box 20, Folder 466)
    - "Big Bull of the West" (Box 20, Folder 467-68)
      See also: Box 4, folder 101; Box 9, folder 248
    - "The Brown Darkness of Germany", 1933 (Box 20, Folder 469)
    - "Columbus of the Air Waves" (Box 20, Folder 470-71)
      See also: Box 9, folder 248; Box 16, 394
    - "Confessions of a Customer's Man", 1931 (Box 20, Folder 472)
    - "Daring Young Man on Wall Street" (Box 20, Folder 473)
      See also: Box 9, folder 248; Box 11, folder 295
    - Essential Rousseau, introduction to, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 474)
    - Knudsen, William S., profile on, 1940-41 (Box 20, Folder 475)
    - Krock, Arthur, profile on (Box 20, Folder 476)
      See also: Box 7, folder 167
    - Matthews, J. B., profile on, 1942, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 477)
    - Powell, Dawn, profile on, 1972, n.d (Box 20, Folder 478)
    - Shipman, Evan, profile on (Box 20, Folder 479-80)
      See also: Box 10, folders 265-66
    - Wheelwright, John Brooks, profile on (Box 20, Folder 481)
      See also: Box 11, folder 288
    - Zugsmith, Leane, profile on (Box 20, Folder 482)
    - Miscellaneous writings
      - Speeches and editorials, 1932-47, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 483)
      - Unidentified fragments, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 484-85)
- Restricted Papers, Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile Papers in box 21 houses fragile originals for which preservation photocopies have been made. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 1, 4, 5, 9, 14, 26, 27 (Box 21, Folder 486)
  - Box 2, folders 29-34 (Box 21, Folder 487)
  - Box 3, folders 56, 57, 63 (Box 21, Folder 488)
  - Box 4, folder 98 (Box 21, Folder 489)
  - Box 5, folders 109, 112, 115, 119, 123, 124 (Box 21, Folder 490)
  - Box 6, folders 139, 156, 160 (Box 21, Folder 491)
  - Box 7, folders 170, 176, 179, 184, 185, 187, 188, 192 (Box 21, Folder 492)
  - Box 8, folders 201, 204, 209, 211, 216, 217, 228 (Box 21, Folder 493)
  - Box 9, folders 237, 241, 248, 250 (Box 21, Folder 494)
  - Box 10, folders 255, 263, 272, 276, 280, 284 (Box 21, Folder 495)
  - Box 11, folders 286, 290, 291, 294, 297 (Box 21, Folder 496)
  - Box 12, folders 317, 319 (Box 21, Folder 497)
  - Box 13, folders 323, 331, 333, 341-43 (Box 21, Folder 498)
  - Box 14, folders 352, 359, 363, 364 (Box 21, Folder 499)
  - Box 15, folders 365, 367, 368, 373 (Box 21, Folder 500)
  - Box 17, folder 406 (Box 21, Folder 501)
  - Box 18, folders 425, 434, 437, 441 (Box 21, Folder 502)
  - Box 19, folders 458, 460 (Box 21, Folder 503)
  - Box 20, folders 475, 477, 482 (Box 21, Folder 504)